Guide to the Benjamin and Julia Stockton Rush Papers, 1766-1845 and undated RL.11044
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Letters, 1777-1824; 1
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to W. Jones [Dr. Walter Jones] (n. p.), 1811 February 12; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 4 pages; 26 cm (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Rush congratulates Jones on his decision to leave Congress, and records his own regrets regarding public service, with particular regard to the funding system and the banks. He now believes American citizens "unfit for and undeserving of liberty."
    United States -- Economic conditions -- 18th century; Political participation -- United States; Political culture -- United States; Monetary policy -- United States -- History -- 18th Century; Jones, Walter, 1745-1815
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Rev. Dr. Samuel Miller (n. p.), 1811 June 7; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 2 Leaves; 7 pages; 33 cm (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Rush writes his memories of John Rodgers, the patriarch of Presbyterianism in the United States. Rodger's had been his boyhood friend at Dr. Finley's school in Maryland. In 1777, Rush had taken care of Rodger's son in Kingston following a battle.
    Miller, Samuel, 1769-1850; Rodgers, John, 1727-1811
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to William Eustis (n. p.), 1811 December 16; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 26 cm (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Rush writes an unsolicited recommendation for Dr. James Mease to serve as head of the Office of Purveyor for the army's medical department.
    Eustis, William, 1753-1825; Mease, James, 1771-1846.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to unidentified, 1812 August 11; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 25 cm (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Purchase, 2012
    Rush's draft letter acknowledges receipt of his certificate of membership in the Royal Academy of Medicine in Madrid, and laments the general lack of appreciation one experiences at the end of a career.
    Medicine -- Practice -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Dr. [David] Hosack (n. p.), 1812 September 25; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 25 cm (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Rush's copy of a letter to Hosack on the origin of the fortifications and other Native ruins in different parts of the country.
    Fortification -- United States -- History; Excavations (Archaeology) -- United States; Historic sites -- United States; Hosack, David, 1769-1835.
  - Benjamin Rush (n. p.) letter to Baron Van Sach (n. p.), 1812 September 28; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 20 cm (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Rush's copy of a letter assuring the Baron he has read all of the medical segments of Van Sach's letters from Surinam, regarding the origins of infectious disease, including yellow fever and influenza. He commends Van Sach on his plans for preventing fevers in Surinam.
    Suriname
  - Benjamin Rush (n. p.) letter to John Thompson (Edinburgh), 1812 October; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 21 cm (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Rush's copy of a letter he wrote regarding his memories of Dr. William Cullen.
    Cullen, William, 1710-1790
  - George Washington (Valley Forge) letter to Benjamin Rush (Yorktown), 1778 January 12; Washington, George, 1732-1799; 2 Leaves; 2 pages; 23 cm (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Washington acknowledges the receipt of Rush's letter, and regrets the defects of the medical department, as Rush and Gov. Livingston have described them. Washington reports that he has taken measures to have the hospitals inspected and considered regulations regarding them. Includes a separate invitation for Rush to dine with the ?Washington.
  - Anthony Wayne (Charlestown) letter to Benjamin Rush (n. p.), 1783 January 20; Wayne, Anthony, 1745-1796; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 23 cm (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Wayne describes his fever and consumption and their treatment, following his loss of blood "in defence of the rights & liberties of America, 'from her coldest, to her hottest sun.'"
    United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783 -- Personal narratives; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813
- Writings, 178[4]-1845 and undated
  Contains a medical case book and a fragment of an essay or lecture written by Benjamin Rush, along with his travel diary for a trip to meet with the Board of Trustees for Dickinson College in 178[4]. Other materials include Julia Rush's devotional journal and exercise book, as well as an undated presentation note written by Richard Rush.
  - Benjamin Rush travel diary, 178[4] April 2-7; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 2 items; 23 pages (Box 3, Folder 1)
    The diary records Rush's travel, accompanied by a servant and via horses, between the outskirts of Philadelphia and Carlisle, Pennsylvania, for an initial meeting with the trustees of Dickinson College. During the meeting the Trustees selected Dr. Charles Nisbet to serve as the College's first president. Rush described the taverns and other travel lodges at which he stopped, along with Tavern staff and other patrons, the quality of the food and drink, along with conversations he witnessed or took part in. Discussion often centered on the topics of the Constitution, paper money, as well as Dickinson College. Rush also described the results of a rapid Spring thaw on the Susquehanna River, the unusually cold weather, the scenery, and the presence whiskey stills in Irish settlements and their impact on their communities.
    5-page transcription available
    Travel writing -- History -- 18th century; Taverns (Inns) -- Pennsylvania -- History -- 18th century.; Pennsylvania -- Description and travel -- 18th century; Pennsylvania -- Social life and customs.; Susquehanna River; Diaries; Dickinson College
  - Benjamin Rush medical casebook, 1811-1812; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 items; 74 pages (Box 3, Folder 2)
    In the casebook, Rush provided brief histories for his treatment of about 75 individuals. Entries generally included the year, patient's name, presented medical issue, dates of treatment, prescriptions applied, pulses noted, and the progression or resolution of the problem. Rheumatism was the most common complaint, along with dropsy (edema), pneumonia, diarrhea, and mania. Among the other illnesses listed were palsy (paralysis), fever, typhus, epilepsy, consumption, scurvy, hydrothorax, swelled spleen, and hysteria.
    Medical records -- Pennsylvania; Physicians -- Diaries; Physicians -- Correspondence; Physicians -- Pennsylvania -- History -- 19th century; Medicine -- Formulae, receipts, prescriptions; Medicine -- United States -- History; Pulse; Rheumatism -- Treatment; Edema -- Treatment; Pneumonia -- Treatment; Diarrhea; Mania
  - Julia Stockton Rush devotional journal, 1812-1845; 222 pages (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Rush not only detailed her religious thoughts and practiced devotional exercises but also outlined her feelings regarding family matters, especially in regard to her bereavement following her husband's death. She requested intersession for family members, such as when her daughters emigrated to England and Canada and their later return, when they suffered serious illnesses, and blessings for the christenings of her grandchildren. She also noted her general physical and mental health as she aged. Entries are irregular, but often annually mark the New Year and her birthday on March 2nd.
  - Benjamin Rush lecture or essay fragments, Undated; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 8 items (Box 3, Folder 4)
    2-page transcription available.
    Lecture or essay regarding use of cordial remedies and bleeding, a discussion of influenza, along with a 2-page partial report on an autopsy that noted the presence of a tumor in the abdomen.
    Herbal liqueurs -- Therapeutic use.; Bloodletting; Influenza; Autopsy; Abdomen -- Cancer.; Abdomen -- Tumors
  - Richard Rush note, Undated; Rush, Richard, 1780-1859; 1 items (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Presentation note for three unnamed items initialed by Richard Rush, son of Bejamin and Julia Stockton Rush.
- Financial Records, 1766-1828
  Includes a few medical statements and receipts, along with two volumes of household accounts maintained by Benjamin Rush, one in conjunction with his wife. Along with general expenses and accounting information, the account books feature the employment records for Rush family staff and servants, often containing comments on the character and notable aspects of the employment history of each employee.
  - Medical statements and receipts, 1766-1810; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; Rush, Julia Stockton; 6 items (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Includes statements and receipts for medicines, advice, consultations, and sundries. In one case, Rush collected a fee on behalf of another physician. Julia Stockton Rush also served as collector, along with her husband. Includes a receipt from Richard Henderson in Leesburg, Va., for payment on the account of Mr. Carter, who had been a patient in Rush's care (see Letters series).
    Medicine -- Practice -- Pennsylvania; Medicine -- Practice -- Accounting; Physicians -- Records and correspondence.; Physicians -- Pennsylvania -- History -- 19th century; Physicians -- Pennsylvania -- History -- 18th Century
  - Household Accounts, 1770-1797; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Volumes; 259 pages (Volume 1)
    Contains primarily Benjamin Rush's records of his expenses, including tax and bond payments, rental property fees, classes and dance lessons for family members, as well as money lent or advanced, accounts paid, cash received, and income from boarders. Rush noted the wide variety of areas where his money was spent, from postage and travel, to clothing and shoes, to household provisions and stores, along with medicines purchased. In addition, Rush created accounts for servants when they arrived, and noted their wages and any increased wages, advances, or loans; cloth, clothing, and shoes provided; with occasional notes on their personal and work habits and work history, and when they exited his service or married. Several of the comments have been redacted, along with a few pages of the account book. Finally, Rush made a few brief commonplace notes randomly in the volume, providing a "style sheet" for description of pulses, outlining a few prescriptions for patients, describing the weather, listing inventories of his furniture and linens, recording a few recipes, and in 1783, noting the news of possible peace with England.
    Finance, Personal -- Pennsylvania -- History -- 18th century; Households -- Pennsylvania -- History -- 18th century; Home economics -- Pennsylvania -- Accounting; Unskilled labor -- Pennsylvania; Rental housing -- Pennsylvania -- 18th century; Taxation -- Pennsylvania.; Account books
  - Domestic Account Book belonging to Benj & Julia Rush beginning June 1799, 1799-1828; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; Rush, Julia Stockton; 1 Volumes; 146 pages (Volume 2)
    Contains primarily accounts for individuals the Rush's employed in their household, including various house servants, cooks, coachmen, farmers and gardeners, along with accounts for work completed by washerwomen outside the residence. Individual accounts include the servant's name, followed by notes on pay and payments made, as well as any holds on pay, advances, loans, and pay rate increases. They also indicated when an individual was supplied with shoes or clothing, or had time off to visit the country. In addition, for the majority of the individuals, Benjamin continued his habit of adding a descriptive note when the person left their service, stating the reason for the departure, commenting on the quality of that servant's work, outlining their personal and work habits (especially their drinking habits), whether they married or not, and their race or ethnic background. Includes an incomplete alphabetical index for servant names. There are a few additional household accounts briefly noted, for wood and an umbrella, as well as two receipts, one for taxes and another (laid-in) for bread.
    Households -- Pennsylvania -- History -- 19th century; Finance, Personal -- Pennsylvania -- History -- 19th century; Home economics -- Pennsylvania -- Accounting; Unskilled labor -- Pennsylvania; Account books
- Legal Documents and Educational Records, 1775-1795
  Present are Benjamin Rush's sworn statement regarding a certificate for Dickinson College, a patent for a tract of land Rush purchased in 1795, along with a certificate of attendance Rush signed for one of his students at the College of Philadelphia Medical School.
  - Samuel Cole educational record, 1775 April 26; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 items (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Rush issued this certificate documenting that Samuel Cole attended 3 courses of his lectures on Chemistry and Pharmacy. Signed by Rush, Professor of Chemistry, College of Philadelphia.
    Medical education -- United States; Student records -- Pennsylvania; College of Philadelphia. Medical School
  - Sworn statement, 1786 April 14; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 items (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Sworn statement that the certificate dated 1 July 1784, payable to Thomas Gilby and signed by John Pierce, is really the property of Dickinson College. signed by Benjamin Rush.
    Dickinson College
  - Land Patent, 1795 April; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 items (Folder 1)
    Land deed for the Williamsburg tract purchased by Benjamin Rush, signed by Gov. Thomas Mifflin and Dep. Sec. James Trimble, with the Pennsylvania State seal, with notice that it was recorded in the state patent books.
    Land tenure -- Pennsylvania -- History -- 18th century; Land titles -- Pennsylvania -- History -- 18th century; Real property -- Pennsylvania -- History -- 18th century; Deeds